hello everybody and welcome back to the
seventh episode of active inference
insights I your host darus PV Wayne and
today I have for the first time two
guests to bring you Vicente Raja is a
research fellow at the University of
meria and affiliate faculty of The
rotman Institute of philosophy at
Western University in Canada his
research lies at the intersection of
philosophy cognitive science
neuroscience and the history of the
Sciences of the Mind in 2021 he was the
first author of the paper the mark of
blanket trick on the scope of the free
energy principle in Act of inference
which argues that quote the Fe is not
the general principle it is claimed to
be and the act of inference is not the
all-encompassing process Theory it is
purported to be either we also have Jeff
Beck Jeff is a computational
neuroscientist studying probabilistic
reasoning in humans and animals he is
also the senior machine learning
research leader versus and is a critical
contributor to the active inference
field writing among others the the paper
Mark of blanket and Mark of blankets and
basian territories guys thank you so
much uh for joining me it's an absolute
pleasure um you know we're talking off
camera there may well be some points of
Divergence but we are four days away
from Christmas at the time of recording
and I think the baby Jesus would want us
to find some
conciliation so we will do we will do
the most we can to strike at differences
and elucidate differences and see uh but
all in the spirit of hopefully
collaborative science and uh
collaborative thinking so in that with
that in mind I think where we could
start is actually where we have no
issues with one another so looking at
that paper where are the kind of points
of just neutral classd this is like a
good starting
point vient I don't know whether you
want to start given you wrote the paper
but where do you
see where Jeff's work or the other key
contributors active influence where do
you see that you know some of the stuff
they say is actually pretty
uncontroversial good question um so
first of all thank you for for for
having me here um um I think I could
start with a very brief detour on why I
wrote this paper or why we wrote uh this
paper on or
even why the paper is the way it is uh
first of all I wrote I started writing
it to actually to make sense of the FP
and active inference for myself right to
to try to see how it was Drive the steps
and actually section two of the paper
remains there just as that right as
starting with a random dynamical system
and just trying to go step by step there
so this is I think one of the points in
which we converge is at least from my
point of view as a a person who works in
the philosophy of the cognitive science
and the cognitive science themselves
that dynamical systems is a good way to
look at cognitive systems so that's I
think we are in kind of the same camp
then uh maybe the modeling strategy that
people like me that comes from radical
embod ctive science and ecological
psychology to model dynamical systems
and the basian twist of it that you find
in active inference are slightly
different right but you know the this
first step this first point I think is a
is a is a point of er conversions to um
but then after after we we made sense we
think of of of of the of the free energy
of the free energy principle and active
inference ER we our point was okay let's
accept all these form ism is good right
we don't challenge it we just accept
like this is
right but even accepting that uh we have
some questions about it that how that
those question have to do more on how
different bits of the formalism relate
to different aspects of cognitive
systems and their relationship with the
environment right um so and I think this
is where the Divergence is
stronger so I think
the convergence has to do with the with
the Primacy I don't know if the premacy
if if if is the word but you know the
attributing importance to a dynamical
systems take on all these issues
and the the good spirit of trying to
find formal methods to study it and our
Divergence I think has more to do with
with uh with with
some conceptions on how to B how to best
address dynamical systems or cognitive
systems in dynamical terms and all that
stuff yeah excellent okay that's that
that's great that's a great start um
Jeff let's go to you let's imagine that
you're reading the mark of blanket trick
for the first time where we will come to
the divergences I promise you well I I I
can tell a story or I can well so I I'll
start in the spirit of this I'll start
off with some with with the point of
agreement that I had with with with the
paper which was one of one of the there
there there are two sort of often
discussed problems with like the FP
literature one is is that it's very it's
it's very it uses idiosyncratic notation
and it can be very difficult to
understand um the other one is I is the
thing that apparently causes a lot of ey
particularly from philosophers and and I
agree that this is a bit of a problem
which is there's a a a penchant for
rhetorical
excess if I could say such a thing which
is a thing I don't think that there's
many many problems with the FP as a
whole but I think that it could be
presented in a more com Compact and
concise way that avoids you know some of
the more philosophical claims that are
often sprinkled throughout these
manuscripts um and I do think that would
create both you know and that this is
something that would create both a bit
more clarity and it's something that
like you know people should poke back to
like when you say like if you find
yourself and this is my personal view
this is not like everyone's everyone who
does this if you find yourself putting
the word thing in scare quotes you might
want to think maybe you're doing
something wrong right it's just sort of
like my knee-jerk
response um and so you know that's that
I think is certainly a point where
there's definitely going to be some
agreement which is is that you know for
me mathematician simplify things be
explicit that's the beauty of it don't
add things to the equations that aren't
necessarily there um but of course
everyone every scientist does this right
we all want to sell our ideas we want to
make we want to make them as big as
possible and so there is some of that
and I think that in particular because
the math is so difficult to understand
and follow right ha you know has um that
those sorts of excesses have become the
Focus right that's easier to sort of
like say oh that's you know this is a
problem this is a problem and so yeah
that's that would be the point of
agreement if I were to quickly and
compactly summarize the point of
disagreement um it's I I will do so by
telling the following story so when I
first came across um Carl FR I was at
the Gatsby at the time and um so Carl
friston was like literally in the
building next door and that's when I
when I first came across him when I saw
him present his stuff and I read a
couple of his papers and and um for me
there were many things that I was like
concerned about let's just leave it at
that let's say concerned we can get into
it more later but the one thing that
wasn't controversial at all in my
opinion was the markof blanket part of
the story and that I think and I and my
hope is is that you know is that as this
conversation proceeds we'll be able to
like I'll be able to explain what I mean
by that um and
maybe come to some sort of consensus so
so I'm happy to do that now but I I feel
like yeah yeah we we we unpick stuff
gradually that's quite that's that's
quite a good irony uh that the markco
blanket was kind of the point of ah this
one this bit works yeah I mean I I take
your point that the maths ought to be
elegant
parsimonious um as much as possible but
unfortunately or or fortunately any gr
unifying Theory comes with it the
philosophy the cognitive science the
Neuroscience the theoretical biology and
so on um and so I think it's an
inevitable consequence that we get
wrapped into epistemological and
ontological questions but we will do our
hardest to unpick them with Simplicity
because I think that's actually all that
we're aiming for so I read the I read
the paper obviously I read it multiple
times and I've read the the commentaries
and and your response to the
commentaries and for me there were about
two or three distinct critiques of the
free energy principle and active
inference that I think we could have a
good conversation about the first is
that Mark of blankets failed to capture
all possible types of conditional
independencies so for example candles
candle relationship to the external
environment or groups of people cultures
societies their relationship to uh the
whatever those external Dynamics are
that they're shielded from by the markco
blanket and then linked to that and then
I'll leave it there is that these things
to use Jeff's quot marks have properties
certain things have properties that
cannot be captured by the mark of
blanket formalism and viente you
mentioned relational properties and
constitutive
self-organization so I don't know
whether you want to take those as two
separate things one being um the
incapacity of the markco blanket to
capture all types of conditional
independencies um and then those two
strands the constitutive
self-organization and the relational
properties I don't know whether you want
to take them separately or whether you
think they fall under the same blanket
if you pardon the pun okay we'll do it
separately Jeff is just pointed to me
let's start therefore with
um incapacity as I said for the mark of
blanket to to capture all conditional
independencies and let's use for sake of
Simplicity this uh object that I
selected before the candle what what
does the candle tell us about the free
energy principle viente please um
actually we we use candle Flames because
it is an example that was in the in in
the in the literat to right it seems if
I remember well I haven't I haven't
reread the
the paper so I might be not fully
accurate about what we claim there but
if I remember well the issue with the
mark of blanket is is is that what we
can take as blanket states are are
changing to fasting time so so so
there's no way to to find them and to
and to know and to and to measure them
over time in in in the way that is
required by the
formalism and if I remember well Thomas
par H talks about it in his in his uh
commentary to the to the to the marcoo
Blan treats it's actually the only
commentary that concedes that we might
be writing something in so which is an
interesting thing but it's okay H and he
claims that it could be solved in if if
in in this kind of of systems or in this
kind of things quotes um
um uh we look to instead of looking to
States themselves we can look to to to
densities of of States you know we can
try to model those States and I think
this is an this is an interesting move
that points out why we think that there
are there is more about the marov
blanket uh than just to say oh no it's
just the simp answer to how to
differentiate this you know the internal
and the external States right the the
the the free energy
principle uh and and active inference
doesn't really tell you whether you have
to choose States or densities of States
as the blanket right so you are putting
assumption extra assumptions there on
how you choose to do that and this is
kind of the overall thread of the
critique when we claim the free energy
principle is not the principle it it
claims to be we we are not claiming that
it cannot be used as the as the as the
principle of Le action to you know to to
write down some equations but that it
seems like just from this principle and
from answering two simple question what
is to be a thing and how to to
differentiate from the environment you
have everything and we try to to to
posit examples in which you always need
an extra step you always need extra
assumptions that that are not always
clear in the in when you only appeal to
the formalism so this is the role of our
of how of why we think that the fact
that candle Flames as a as an example
that was in the in the literature why
candle flames are important I think they
point out that you always need you
always need extra assumptions that are
not always clear in the in when you only
appeal to the formalist great um perfect
that's a really nice exposition of of
the claim that you're making uh Jeff
I'll jump to you then um it would be you
know uh R talk to that would be
wonderful and I think actually with
specific mention if possible of this
dichotomy that viente mentioned which is
are we talking about States some kind of
ological thing again or we talking about
probability densities and where does
that line become blurry what actually is
that difference or is it just are we
just making a kind of false identity
claim what what's the sort of what's
really going on
here um so I think that the best way the
best way to respond is would be so the
the the short the short piy and
dismissive answer is to say I I solved
the pro I solved the flame problem I
wish I could share my screen I have some
really cool like I have some really cool
graphics um so what one of the one of
the other problems that that that and
when conveying the fre free energy
principle that um its its proponents
have faced is the fact and I sort of say
this the math is really hard and in
order to in order to make it tractable a
lot of additional assumptions get put in
along the way just to make the math
easier right and some of those
assumptions
are necessary to make you know many of
those assumptions are not actually part
of the free energy principle by itself
right or part of the marov blanket story
on its own right but are done to make
the math easier like when I first came
across the FP I thought there was no
difference between active inference and
KO control
theory right and the reason why was
because when they go to actually solve
the equations they make some additional
assumptions to make the math easier so
that it ends up being equivalent to KO
control theory but if you go in and sort
of say well what actually is the
principle itself as derived either as
Carl does it from um
uh statistical physics or the way I
prefer to do it which is directly from
information Theory right that's not the
case right the actual like objective
function of active inference and allv
solving these like complicated path
integrals and things like that but to
make the problem easier to make the math
easier to make it more solvable
additional like factorial assumptions
are built in and a lot of people jump on
the fact that like oh it's like you have
all these additional assumptions they
kind of like but those are done often
for like computational reasons they're
not necessarily part of the we like to
joke that you know you know everybody
talks about the generality of the path
integral formulation of and and Jan's
maxent and how it's mappable on thisal
physics what people often forget is the
problem with the path interal
formulation is you actually have to
solve path inters which is a serious
pain in the butt and so this is sort of
like my summary I what one of the things
that has contributed to a lot of
confusion has been these additional
mathematical simplifications that are
then taken to be part of the theory when
they are not um in regards to the flame
story because I know I gave like a a py
and dismissive answer and I'd like I
don't you know that was
just I will fix that now in the interest
of politeness um one the reason that I
didn't think that the marov blanket
story was like at all controversial was
because of its link to systems
identification Theory right the Markov
blanket
itself basically just specifies the
domain in which systems identification
Theory can
apply right so the idea is so what so
how does it so when you I don't have you
know so system environment inputs
outputs right if you're doing systems
identification Theory you're basically
saying well what is the system doing how
what is its input output this is very
colloquially right we can make this more
what is it it's input output
relationship in order to do systems
identification Theory right you need to
know what that input output relation
that's the goals to figure out what that
input output Rel and if you see a
particular input output relationship
that gives you the label for that kind
of system right it's a system of Type X
because it has this input output
relationship the markof blanket is
basically just specifies the domain in
which you are going to do a statistical
version of systems identification Theory
right it's the domain of the inputs and
outputs of so when somebody says I have
a big system and there's lots of stuff
in it and I'm going to segregate out a
little system from it the mere fact that
you can do that to when you say like
this is a subsystem you have already
said that there's a Markov
blanket does that make sense right all
subsystems have blankets like by
definition it's it's it's sort of implic
that's and that's why I never thought
that it was controversial because what
do we do we want say well that's a
subsystem that's an important thing it
gets its own label and so it has a
blanket it's like it's it's it's just
it's the way we do systems
identification Theory so I don't know I
want to hear if I want to see if
Vincente has a response before I move on
to the flame in particular I mean that
that's that's kind of
I that's that's that's the that's what I
read when I when I was reading the
literature more uh it's kind of it's
it's it's it's h noncontroversial for
the people who work on it in that sense
like you you you identify a system uh
there therefore there's there's there's
a blanket and there's an external State
I think and part of the Marco blank
trick is to see different issues we find
with that that that for many systems we
are interested in we don't see it to be
so straight forward like we when when we
model with dynamical
systems for instance with the hkb model
H to the the behavior of two couple
oscillator where the where the
collective variable is relative
pH our system is the couple oscillators
so you can put a blanket around it I
guess but then what's the
environment uh it's it's it's the it's
the blanket put on the face of space of
the relative
face which is not a property of any of
the two things there right so I mean I
kind of understand the abstract sense
but then I don't exactly see how this
apply to kind of systems that we are
interested in right so I I I'll just
quickly respond so so the problem with
the whole Markov blanket part of the
story is that there's just two goddamn
many marov blankets right you have this
big complicated system
right and even you know and even if
you're going to limit yourself as they
often do in the FP literature to like
static Markov blankets right where one
once a particle or constituent component
or whatever has been assigned to either
environment blanket or object it's
always there right so this is a
situation where there's no such thing as
matter transfer right which is why the
flame Case by the way like doesn't work
right the flame the Flames have Markov
blankets but they're not static right
because as the matter you know as it
burns and moves in and fuel comes in and
and exhaust goes out right the matter is
constantly so if if your definition of a
blanket is that it's tight to matter
then yeah you're right like you can't do
a flame at all but that's so but putting
that issue aside the problem with Mark
blank is is that they're everywhere you
have a glass of water every single fluid
element in the glass of water so what's
a fluid element right you take a glass
of water you draw a little circle I mean
obviously it's not it's 3D right but but
an arbitrary fluid volume has a blanket
right and we and and we know this like
when we do finite element methods for
simulating them we draw the we take our
glass of water and we make it into lots
of little cubes and all the cubes are
connected and the boundaries between the
cubes form the blanket there's too many
blankets blankets are absolutely
everywhere right and they and their
boundaries are often completely like
where you're going to put your blanket
is the hardest problem to solve right
and I think that that that the free
energy literature has not worried too
much about the problem of where you're
drawing the blanket because the idea was
if you've got a blanket then it's
subsystems have blankets right we're
interested in subsystems and so now we
can just like put that problem aside but
it's a really difficult problem to say
well what is the principle that tells me
that this gets a
blanket right why why is a blanket
that's around you know a bubble Rising
through my glass of water the right
blanket as opposed to an arbitrary
blanket around a fluid element that has
no bubbles in it right and I don't think
that that that that question has not
been adequately addressed in the you
know you know in my opinion but I
believe that that there is a notion that
is sort of implicit in the Fe
approach that handles that and so when
when I when I sat down and tried to
solve the flame problem I asked myself
well what additional principle and this
might make vincenta happy right there is
an additional principle he was
absolutely right I think the principle
was implicit um but the additional
principle is like how do you choose your
blankets well you choose them for
parsimony and simplicity right in other
words we use the scientific method right
you take all the ways that you you have
this complicated interacting system you
take all the ways that you could draw
the you know boundaries in them and
there's like an uncount you know not
uncountable but there's a really large
number of different ways that you could
draw your blankets and the way you pick
the one that's important is the one that
results in the greatest simplification
of the of the resulting Dynamics this is
basically like mean you can think of
this as being field or course graining
if you're a physicist right that's what
course graining is is that you segregate
your system into macroscopic variables
or macroscopic components if it's a ma
mechanical system and the choice that
you make as to how you're going to do
that is to is to basically make the
system as simple as possible if you take
that approach then you have if you take
that approach and apply it to the flame
situation in particular that's exactly
what you discover right you discover
that the blanket of a flame right is
just outside the reaction Zone where all
of the exothermic reactions are going on
okay excellent no I think we're agreeing
too much um I think that's going very
well um I love the the flame problem I
like that yeah gorgeous I I really wish
I could share my screen because I like
queued up some videos and like you know
and and had some figures that I was like
just in case the flame case really is
cool I'm gonna publish that soon I'm
just working on I'm trying to get like a
whole I'm working on a
um I took some fake I took some data
from you guys know what particle lenia
well you know everyone knows what
Conway's Game of Life Is So This is
Conway's Game of Life but for
interacting particles and so they get
these particles to do cool things and so
you can put in a random bunch of
particles and they form a cell membrane
and the cell membrane grows stuff like
fella and so we applied it to that
situation as well and what you find is
that the blankets are changing over time
and as they change the identity of the
object also changes which is exactly
what you want right and the reason for
this is because the blanket itself the
blanket alone is meaningless right it
just specifies the domain in which
you're going to do your system
identification or dimensionality
reduction right what really defines an
object's type is the statistics of the
domain right and so as a result you can
watch these cells evolve and as the
statist as the statistics of the various
boundaries in the system because there's
more than one um change so does theide
identity of the associated object right
which is really what want this is really
all about labeling stuff right right and
in order to label stuff by type you need
a blanket and the way that you identify
a type is by the statistics of the
blanket okay this is really useful um
because yeah I think we found agreement
with the idea that the Fe needs to
integrate some historicity some Dynamics
and perhaps even changing identities of
you as you've just outlined there Jeff I
think yeah well I think the the critical
thing is is recogn and this is implicit
in everything that Carl writes right
it's it it just needs to be made more
explicit right he says the blanket
defines the phenotype that is a
misleading statement it's true but it's
misleading right the correct statement
is the statistics of the blanket Define
the phenotype right right it's not just
the blanket itself that the blanket
itself is just a domain yeah right it's
just where yeah so yeah well I think
this is a um this problem I think has
started to be remedied within the active
inference literature um because I don't
know if you guys have noticed this as
well but there's been a move to turn the
internal generative model to a
generative model that actually both
encompasses across the mark of blanket
the external and the internal States so
this is something that Maxwell Ram makes
very clear in his um in this year's
paper um physics of belief to put it
roughly um but I think that there is
there is still a slight point of
difference here and I wonder whether
it's just a semantic one
Jeff you still talk about internal
States or the particle the thing the
system and the
environment whereas visente is talking
about coupled oscillators and the way
that I think about this is we can either
have an intrinsic or an extrinsic
relation between let's say external
Dynamics and internal Dynamics now what
does that mean well an external relation
would be something like a causal
relationship so the A and B retain their
identity despite the fact that they're
causally related an intrinsic relation
is something more like a familiar
relation okay if I am uh my you know my
mother is defined as my mother because
of the relationship that she has with me
so in many in many ways I find that this
distinction that you guys are carving
here might be neatly mapped on to that
distinction benter I'm going to start
with you do you think that a mistake
that the fvp makes might be to try and
carve out an external
relation so we've got a enacting
changing B which changes a when really
the focus should be on the Dynamics of
the entire system as a whole in the way
that sort of Evan Thompson and um those
who followed spoke about these kind of
couple Dynamic systems where the
identity is in the mutual
coupling good question I mean I would
like to to just point out I think Jeff
has
pointed uh has pointed out uh what our
issue is um and and I agree with with
pretty much everything he he has said in
that in that regard right our issue
basically was that I mean we have
nothing against marov blanket blankets
as a as a methodological tool as a
mathematical tool but we would like to
know more about how you select the
blanket because we think that depending
on how you select the blanket you are
interested in you be doing two different
things right and and and that and that
it's there are it's other parts other
fundamental parts of your theory what
makes you to to to select a blanket
let's say for the
organism uh and then the organism has
internal States and the environment is
the external States or if you are an
ecological psychologist like me you want
a blanket for the organiz environment
system and then everything is internal
State and it's not clear what the what
the what the external state would be
there right you can also choose a
blanket on the organiz environment
system and a nested one and another
blanket it's it's blankets all the way
down man all the way to protons they got
blankets too so as as a mathematical
tool so to speak there are too many
blankets right yeah but how you choose
them reflects what kind of what kind of
fundamental Theory you have in mind and
when I say fundamental Theory I think
about psychology cognitive science right
so
um if you for instance think that the
organism has this input output mapping
and all the relevant computations
happens inside so all the control of
behavior all all the are all the all the
all the perceptual inference is
depending on the internal States you you
are first you
are likely
a cognitive scientist of the mainstream
right and you want the the blanket in
the organism and the external states are
basically
input right uh while if you are an
eological
psychologist and you think that to
understand the perception for instance
the first step is to see the structors
in the
environment those structors are relevant
in themselves and contribute to
perception as much as the internal
states of the organism there so then you
probably don't take those structures to
be just input right
so my my point being here that I totally
agree that there are too many
blankets and that this selection process
depends on deeper
theories that go maybe beyond the free
energy Principle as such and you can
then you can use the free energy
Principle as a method to to develop
those those theories right yeah so yeah
so this is the I I mean my take on this
is so I I completely agree right there
there is a sort of hidden additional
principle but I think that one of the
reasons this got neglected in the free
energy literature is because the whole
point was
we're always drawing blankets you can
draw it anywhere and this Theory still
applies right doesn't matter where you
put your blanket right I can still I can
still treat the system as if it is doing
inference over its environment it does
you know exact you know that that that
was sort of like I think the reason why
the the sort of additional like how do
you select your blanket problem was
neglected was because they were trying
to show the principle always works right
um that's sort of my my my defense of of
of of of Carl friston's world is that
like there's a reason they skipped the
problem because wasn't the important
problem right the important problem was
it doesn't matter how you draw your
blankets you still get you still can
apply the rest of the principle so if
you decide that that your system is a
cell that's fine if it's a collection of
cells that still works if it's it and so
on
right so our question was then I I think
this question was in the Marco blancet
trick too what if your blanket is the is
the is the organism environment system
what are the external states to that
system that the system INF first so to
speak if yeah if if you're if you're
yeah so if your blanket is like the
whole universe I don't I'm gonna go with
it's Christmas I'm gonna go with baby
Jesus okay very good right
no right I mean you know the so I think
that that's counter to the to to the
reason why we want to Define blanket in
the first place and the reason is
because we want to label
things right and the reason we want to
label things is you know is because well
it it simplifies our lives right if I
can look and say that's a cat that's
another kind of cat right then not you
know I can sort of use you know that you
know use those labels because they make
my my life easier right they make
prediction easier about what's going to
happen and things like that right that's
the reason why we want to have labels
and the mark s well you know this is a
potential place so that and the reason I
make this because I do think that
implicit in the whole approach while not
necessarily as explicitly made in the
literature as it should have been is
that the goal is to label things the
goal is to come up with phenotypes and
since the goal is to come up with
phenotypes you can ask the question well
why would we want to do that and the
answer is parsimony right we want a
simple compact representation of our
world and the way we do it is by taking
big complicated things made of lots of
little parts and giving them a single
label that describes a lot of their
General properties and features and that
is exactly what the mark out blanket
does or is capable of doing and so that
also tells you which is why like in my
world right that's the additional PR it
was implicit I'm I want to make it
explicit that the way that we choose
which blankets to focus on is like the
way we do science it's based on
simplifying Dynamics for the purposes of
prediction and data
compression Jeff I may jump in here um
and perhaps speak on vincente's behalf
I'm very happy for him to jump over me
and and and clarify this but I think a
question comes up here which is so we're
interested in labeling we're interested
in describing coupled
systems so how come when in the FP
literature we draw blankets they so uh
coincidentally happen to fall elegantly
on what we intuitively believe to be
things and their blankets so for example
yes you say okay it's because well we
see cats and glasses and humans and
planets and like why wouldn't we carve
blankets around them but why in a sense
does it work to carve blankets around
them if we're dealing more in
information exchange than how the object
appears to our sensorium and given that
as a mathematician or a physicist what
does that say about the mapping between
kind of our perception and the
information transfer that we're being
able to describe via the Marco
blanket
I think very hard about that question
um because my my knee-jerk response is
to like is to launch into my like what
is science for discussion which is
probably not going to directly address
uh what it is that you what what it is
that you want me to to address
um
when
when the issue is still if the issue is
still like
um let's see so there are two there are
two things going on here right one is
what do we do with the information that
the Universe gives us how do we
categorize it label it and make it
simple and easy to understand and then
the other issue is is well what is NE
you know what is any subsystem
necessarily doing right and those are
very different issues right when we talk
about the when we ask the question
though why do we call this a subsystem
and and you know and then like I'm
trying to cut it in half and like this
not and and this not a subsystem and
that choice is arbitrary right that's
one of the the lessons that I'm trying
to drive home here is is that like you
can draw a blanket around anything the
question is why would
you right having drawn a blanket all of
the free energy mechan the basian
mechanics all apply right but why why
would I draw a particular blanket and it
really is because it's useful to us
right if we could just like have a
computer that simulated absolutely
everything right and that didn't and it
was like I don't know it cost like five
cents to run we would totally do that
and we would be happy and we wouldn't
care about labels right but we don't
have that ability right we are trying to
construct these you know things that we
can wrap our brains around we're trying
to simplify things you know to make them
parsable and understandable to us and so
that's why we would choose a particular
set of blankets now but again the point
though is and the reason why I think
that there wasn't enough emphasis in the
free energy literature is that all of
once you have established that there's a
blanket which you can always do right
the rest of it just
follows right all the stuff about you
know is it effectively doing is it
behaving as if it's performing inference
on its environment yes right I think the
more interesting question that Vincente
brings up in the paper which which which
I read
yesterday that I thought was a really
great question um was had to do with
with well which is the environment and
which is the object
right because even this parsimony
principle that I just established right
doesn't help with that because I just
said simplify the global Dynamics like
what what you know what what um
macroscopic Theory does the best that
happens to have this partitioning um and
that doesn't tell you which is the but
this is but this is where I think you
now need to move back into physics land
right so people like I I really like the
work of Jeremy England um and
uh and everyone loves like shinger
little I is it what is life is that the
title of it right um where there is you
know in in in that work there is like a
a definition of how you there is a
notion of how you tell which is the
agent and which or which is the object
and which is the environment which is
the agent and which is the environment
and it basically has to do with energy
flow right so you could sort of say oh
well you know the organism is the thing
that takes in energy and prod produces
enty right and that once you've done
that if you're talking about a physical
system right you know then now you have
something that that does in fact
uniquely identify you know which is
which which you don't get out of then
this is my point right you don't get
that out of a out of a Simplicity
parsimony type
principle right I'm not sure whether you
wanna yes go that second point or
whether you want to loop back to my
first point about the mapping between
the supposedly arbitrary epist logical
tool based approach of the Marco blanket
and actually maybe how that maps onto
onto logically at least what we perceive
I don't know which one you want to start
with yeah I think that that that the the
last uh thing or did this last in
intervention by by by je I think it he
States and I think we we are going to
agree here he he literally States the
Marco blancet trick right that that as
as as soon as you put the blanket on top
of a system right or whatever you choose
with all this uh pragmatic stuff then
you can do Bas inference right you as
you put the blanket you have now the so
to speak the data structure with latent
variables observables
and internal ones to do that and I think
we agree that or we could agree that
this is the Marco blanket trick while
Jeff thinks this is good right uh it's
it's it's it's good we think it's so so
right but that kind kind kind of
be the point right so I think the Marco
blancet trick is
good if you are already convinced for
instance that uh perception is a kind of
inference and then it gives you very
precise mathematical tools to model
that now if you think like
some crazy people like me right
that perception is not something that
you know something that the internal
states of an
organ the internal State states of an
organism do in order to know the
external States so to speak
but is a property of the organism
environment
system then this data structure doesn't
really map very well with what we want
to do or maybe it does but we don't see
how and and and part and part of of our
paper is to is to try to to express you
know to to state these doubts on okay
how could apply this if I think this s
thing
right and uh and then second part uh
which is what the what the um why the
blanket falls exactly where it needs to
to be I think this is a part of first
this is a part of a conversation I've
had like dozens of time
with Maxwell right he he's he's the
person I've talked more about this so
gve talk about this and actually in in
their commentary to the Marco blanket
trick they talk about this uh paper he
has with dton the weak marov blankets
right that they prove that there are a
lot of them right like like as soon as
you have Dimensions you know
and and our question in our response was
yes I mean but the point is not that you
have a lot of them it's how you choose
the right one so how you choose for
let's say for the visual system how you
choose the blanket in the sensory
receptors so to speak right and and I
think Jeff has been touching upon that
right in in in in in some of some of the
things he he has been saying
today before I move back to Jeff could
you just maybe for the audience expound
upon what you meant by this sort of
Distinction um Mak sense when we take
for granted perception as inference I
think that would be quite an interesting
Avenue just to unpick a little bit
further just so audience knows exactly
what you mean by that yeah so
uh long story short uh the common theory
of perception at least since handhold
but most likely seem the cart or even
beyond that is that ER perception is is
a is a form of inference right so the
our mind brain is in the business of
inferring the real environment so to
speak
from impoverished stimulation so what we
get in in in a our sensory systems is
usually ER ambiguous not not not very
informative or not completely
informative and
generally uh unsufficient as to know
what is the exact cost of the of that
input right like the typical examp ex is
is that is that you know a a a small
close object can give you the same input
that than a larger object that is
farther away right they can occupy the
same angle in your in your retina blah
blah so the mainstream theory is that
the brain is in the business
of inferring the real properties of the
environment from this impoverished input
and it that's so because it it can use
uh prior knowledge memory experience you
know to build up and good model of the
real
environment ecological psychologists
think ER along with many other people
that come that come at least from
Willian James Willian James explicitly
claims that the kind of um of approach
this inferential approach to perception
is pure mythology I I mean it's kind of
the way they wrote in the 19th century
right
but the point being is that for
ecological psychologists the kind of
prior knowledge you need in order for
the inference to work is very difficult
to
justify um so they think
that perception is more of a relation of
Rich information that comes from the
environment and the and the internal
Dynamics and the relation itself is what
uh perception is but we don't need an
inference because we don't need to go
from impoverished stimulation to the
real environment but the the there's a
way to understand
perceptual information that gives you
all you need without the need of
prior knowledge
in order to get grips so to speak with
the Real Environment so it's kind of a
direct undirect staff or perception as
an inference or perception as an as
information detection now I have to put
again because I've talked with Maxwell a
lot about this so I just want to put
a uh so sort
of um
here right you can still see how the
internal Dynamics change in order to
couple with these and
reach information in terms of some form
of basian inference because basan
inference is yes you know you can you
can describe the the path of a dynamical
system towards an attractor in terms of
a probability density of the St so
there's there's a form to to maybe
there's a form to use inference that is
the ban inference way in which Zan
capture both of them I'm still in an
ongoing discussion with maxw about yeah
this is this is the as if part of the
free energy principle right the math
tells us that everything right behaves
as if it is performing basy and
inference right it doesn't tell us two
additional things like how shitty that
inference
is it could be real like a rock is per
forming Basi and inference it's just not
doing a very good job um and uh you know
but it but that's but that's that that
just follows that just Falls entirely
from the mathematics up right is that is
that it is an as if description right
the description of
anything you know it is always an
available description of a phenomenon
that it is that it functions as if it's
performing inference right um whether or
not it's actually performing inference
or doing like solving the right
inference problem or or however you want
to put that um is not is not explicitly
addressed and I think a really
interesting question it you know so for
example when you know when one applies
the the free energy principle in
practice there's always this implicit
assumption that whatever the thing is
doing is it's actually doing inference
correctly right there's an optimal
inference engine sort of like hidden
inside now they can get away with this
right because what goes on on the inside
doesn't matter right and what defines
the object is the what defines the thing
is the statistics of its boundary and so
if you have like a really boring
boundary statistics like you're a rock
right then you don't need a very
sophisticated like like the inference
engine that you would actually use to
sort of say well what is the you know
what does this rock have to infer about
the external World in order to be a rock
and the answer is very little so you
kind of get a lot of these things for
free but it is an as if description
right it's not like you know it's it's
just and you know but like I this is you
know another way to get to the free
energy principles from a purely
information theoretic approach right and
I prefer that approach because all of
this stuff makes a little bit more sense
right you're not sort of saying like the
rock is doing inference you're saying
you know the rock is behaving as it
becomes more clear that this is sort of
an as if argument right as opposed to
it's there's literally an internal state
in the rock that is Computing you know
the probability that the that the water
in the Stream is about to change no it's
not right okay yeah I I had only because
have to in order to be a rock yeah yeah
yeah I um I was did a quite a good
podcast with Adam saffron a couple of
days ago and I said my favorite two
words in the free energy principle are
looks
like um but as as if is that as if as if
is the one that I like to pick up yeah
as if looks like uh no I think that's I
think that's useful
clarification um unless you're a pan
psychist and then they might be coming
for you um what's wrong with pan
psychism I don't understand why
everyone's down on hey I I actually
don't mind that I'm kind of into the
spookier versions but well they might
they might be Keen to perhaps I can't
speak for Philip Goff and everyone else
but they might be Keen to bring into
question the validity of that as if or
looks like but we need not go there um I
wanted to sort of I do want to this was
one of the critiques that I kind of
identified so I do want to just get some
clarity on it um and I I'll actually
quote Vicente here so this is vicente's
response to the commentary
um the extent to which something counts
as a thing depends on the choice of
Market Mark of blanket partition which
can be adjusted according to the needs
of the model there is an ambiguity here
on the one hand it is claimed that
things are what they are by definition
even if boundaries do not real align
with the intuitive ones for ordinary
things on the other hand when the Fe
presents possible examples of things
like brains or cells the mark of blanket
always falls in the right place from the
intuitive point of view so that probably
puts more elegantly the point I was
trying to make
earlier je does that shed any Clarity on
where I was going and Jeff do you think
you do you have a kind of repul to that
I I almost hate to do what I'm about to
do can you can you give me the quote one
more time my bra I'll give you I'll give
you the that was was a lengthy quote and
I'm gonna need to hear it one more time
to fully absorb and appreciate it I'll
do a sort of amended version a shortened
version on the one hand it is claimed
that things are what they are by
definition even if the boundaries do not
really align with the intuitive ones for
ordinary things on the other hand when
the FP presents possible examples of
things like brains or cells the mark of
blanket always falls in the right place
from the intuitive point of
view okay so I do have a response to
that and that this goes back to the
notion that what defines a thing where
you get this sort of notion of phenotype
is the statistics of the
blanket and so that gives you the
ability to sort of say oh this is like
you know like right now I'm I'm I'm
concerned with brains so I all I have to
do is ask what is the statistics you
know what is these statistics of the of
the brain blanket right and then that's
the thing I'm currently going to
investigate right and so you know what
but I do think that this does illustrate
the you know one of the issues which
we've been talking about which is that
like there is this sort of fundament you
know if you were going to like denovo
start just putting blankets on
everything in the world right there
isn't an explicit principle present in
the FP that tells you how to do that
right there's this additional principle
which is like you know that that that I
that that led to the you know the
algorithm that I used to discover the
blankets of flames which is like
parsimony right but it's it's not now
now the reason why that that they don't
worry about that is because it's the
implicit in every single thing in the FP
literatures noce that we are labeling
stuff right I have the freedom to label
what I'm interested in and having done
that right that sort of tells me what
the blanket statistics are going to be
um I'll just add one other thing the
reason I prefer like the the information
theoretic derivation of the Fe is
because is is because um the way that
works is you start out with a
probability distribution over blankets
right it's like this is like is and you
take it's a it's a it's a ma it's a
James Max cow or Max ENT kind of
approach and you sort of say like hey
like I have some laws that tell me how
the universe works and those are some
constraints right and then I also have I
want to find I want to find some subset
of my system that has these statistics
those statistics are then definitional
this leads to you know sort of Levan
equation type things right that you can
then solve which tells you how the world
has to be how the individual particles
in the system have to behave if you're
doing it in particle space um in order
for that thing to exist right and it has
to exist because you imposed it as a
constraint when you did your sort of Max
entty thing
right um if you have it if you have that
in mind what you're really asking when
you sort of when you take this sort of
Fe you know when you we sort of we if
you take this sort of
um can I can I use the phrase
ontological potential or is that g to
make people upset right one of the
things that comes out if you if you take
this sort of free approach you're
basically like look these statistics
Define an object
type right and now what I want to know
is I want to know like well what what's
inside what's outside like what kind of
environment can it live in like what
kind of comp you know you know what what
does it have to be made of right you can
just apply that those statistics as part
of a constraint do Max ENT and get all
of the equations that tell you how what
kind of environment this sort of thing
can live in right but the starting point
was like I'm interested in like this
kind of thing right and the reason why
we call it an ontological potential is
because you sort of said like you've
You' started by saying this is my
definition of something and free energy
is literally a potential
function like when you do it in this Max
nway it's literally a potential function
so free energy is an ontological
potential but it does start by saying
this is the thing this is the thing I'm
interested in it starts by specifying
those statistics the statistics of a
given object
type do you want to add anything to that
I mean I'm wondering whether from a
philosophical if you're putting a
philosophical hat on what presos
positions just that kind of as as Jeff
said like we're starting from like this
is a thing what philosophical
presuppositions does that uh
entail yeah I
mean
uh
I'm I'm kind of happy with that right
you choose your thing and you you you
apply the methods you want to so I'm we
we we we really don't have anything with
when I see with the authors of of of of
the paper of course but myself also uh
we really don't have
any
any uh criticism to
that
our uh criticism and actually it was
that paper was published along with a
few more that were talking about that
there's this this this one by J Brun Cal
on theer blanket and Miguel agilera and
Chris Bley had another one there right
um
so so to speak if you are a front with
look this is what I took to be what I
take to be a thing or this is my thing
of of interest for these reasons and
then I'm I'm going to apply the Marco
blanket here if the methods work go you
know like cool uh the thing is that
sometimes in the literature these extra
steps or these parts are as Jeff are
just have said not explicit enough so it
seems that everything follows from you
ask what is to be a thing and then you
have a full theory of
cognitive neuroscience and we are like
we don't think so right there are other
other other deep ideas that word there
right and but if we go back to the to
the to that
quote
um it's also not about the kind of the
the the general possibilities of the
free energy principle and active
inference and the Marco
blanket formalism but more about how it
is presented in the literature sometimes
right so sometimes it is clear that you
put the blanket so in so to speak in the
in the space not in the real space but
in you know you you you select some
states and then you put the blanket
there and this is clear for instance in
one paper I think it's Michael kirchof
Julian kerstein Carl fron and I don't
know if I and if I if I forget someone
else but they actually modeled couple
the pendulums right and the blanket
states there where something I'm not
completely sure but where something like
velocity
and yeah ration or position acceleration
these are not the the intuitive ones
right this is not the the the surface of
of of of the pendulum so to speak but
then when you go to any figure in the in
the in in in the literature you see the
blanket that is in the in the sensory
receptors or or or or or in the membrane
of of of of the cell when you
expect the blanket would will be from an
intuitive point of view so our point is
that the these two claims seems to be
not very well aligned right either you
find the blanket in an in an abstract
state of space or or or or in
an space of states or or or or or in an
N dimensional states of space and then
the blanket can be velocity acceleration
jerk whatever you want right or you go
to the more intuitive uh way in which
you know the the blanket of the cat is
you know I guess the hair or something
like that or you find a way which which
I guess is the is the is the is the
ultimate aim right you find a way to
align these two
maybe but I I think the reason that this
happens though is because because the
principle is uniformly applicable to all
systems and you know by and all sub
systems and all subsystems of subsystems
they kind of like glossed over that
problem it's like doesn't matter what
system you're interested in this Theory
applies right and I think that's one of
the reasons why like the issue that
Vincente brings up was basically glossed
over right it's because it it was it
wasn't you know the the the the two
interesting questions from my
perspective that got glossed over are
how do blankets form in the first you
know how do the blankets that we would
like to call blankets because they're
blankets everywhere but how are the
interesting how do interesting blankets
form right what are the what are the
mechanics that that lead to that process
and then why do we say this is an
interesting blanket then that is just a
a drop of or just
a fluid
volume blanking on the easy stuff now
why why yeah why is that just a fluid
why is that an uninteresting blanket and
this is where the whole like parsimony
thing comes in right interesting
blankets have interesting properties
right and they simplify the overall
Dynamics but that but but if you if you
if you start out your paper by writing
that like oh well I'm gonna have this
other principle and it's gonna say this
is a blanket and this is the preferred
blanket right then you sort of if it it
kind of tarnishes your ability to say
that your theory is uniformally
applicable to all systems and subsystems
and I think that that is ultimately the
cause of this of of this particular
confusion you know which is why like you
know know like when I saw this stuff my
knee-jerk response was I why are they
saying a flame doesn't have a
blanket right so my I I I should mention
my my uh the title of my PhD thesis was
like what was it complex Dynamics and
solid flame micro structure oh actually
burning
stuff and and the way that we model
Flames is explicitly with a blanket the
blankets you know is is is there the
flame it's burning this way down a fuse
like this I think Acme bomb right it's
going like this it's going down a fuse
and there's a blanket right the blanket
is basically just outside the reaction
zone right in the same way that like you
know fluid flowing or air going by like
an airplane wing forms a little boundary
which we call curiously enough the
boundary layer right um and you know and
that's a blanket too we are constantly
using blankets because they simplify
Dynamics and that was exactly how I got
to this you know that's exactly why to
me that there was this implicit
parsimony principle that solved that
particular problem excellent um but but
I but I certainly agree like you know it
was it was a rhetorical choice right you
want to show that it it always applies
so of course I'm just going to randomly
draw blankets as you know as need
be because it always
works I I like that you know in the in
the in
the I mean in the in the spirit of
generality they kind of glows over these
tiny details that there are some systems
that might be tricky right but I think
there's kind of
another reason for that I don't think
it's a it's a it's an opposite one it's
a it's a complimentary one but and and
it's a reason that I think applies um
mostly to Psychology and
Neuroscience um like like Jeff I don't
I'm not a super fan of the of what what
they call the high road to to the to the
fre princip yeah the the random
dynamical system plus I like uh better
the one that comes from predictive
processing and builds up right first uh
because I think it it is it it what
happened historically right with the
with the with the 1990s paper on how to
encoders to you know and you can see
that and then uh
because
it makes explicit how the free energy
principle within Psychology and
Neuroscience grows within a
theory within an overall theory in which
this separation is already taken for
granted right you see there are the
internal states of of of which are the
brain that are making the inference
there are some blanket States right
which are receptors and there's some
environment there so right so right this
kind
of
blanket formalism perfectly fit the
overall idea that there we have internal
states that have to infer the external
one so it was not an issue for kind of
say the mainstream psychology
Neuroscience to think in that way it was
like taking for for for for granted so
to speak but then this there's this
weird Weir weird people call ecological
psychologist that have issues with that
thing and and and of course that's from
that's the place from from where our
paper comes right we see issues in that
in some systems in that in that so so so
I'm gonna propose like The Happy The
Happy Middle Ground here right so so the
statement that all things behave as if
they are performing inference is kind of
hard to get around right because like it
it literally follows from I mean it's it
it follows from whether you take
statistical physics or information
Theory it's sort of a statement about
like an but what what it doesn't tell
you is the thing that is is what it
doesn't you know so now you say well I
don't think the brain is doing inference
or I don't think perception is inference
or something like that it turns out
that's not incompatible with with with
what the free energy principle states
either and the reason for this is
because the free energy principle says
that all things behave as if they are
performing inference it says nothing
about the quality of that
inference it could be really shitty
inference it has to be good enough so
that the thing can maintain its boundary
statistics the the statistics that
Define it as like that type of a thing
but it could in fact be really bad
compared to what a normative model of
inference would be would be performing
and I think this step this step has also
been been sort or this this little bit
has also sort of been been missed right
there there in a lot of applications
because like especially like what I do
nowadays which is like you know AI
applications you don't want to find
systems that do shitty inference right
you want to find systems that do optimal
imprints right and so but but but in
practice right that that becomes the new
question sort of like well okay so
they've shown that it's always doing
inference and I'll just accept that but
I don't care I don't care because I'm
interested in the exact in in the kinds
of inference mistakes that it's making
right it's kind of like saying like when
we're in the lab right so we I've worked
with a lot of Behavioral scientists over
the years and when they're in the lab
they always sit the monkey down and okay
let's not do monkeys uh there's a mouse
and the mouse is doing some task and we
always want to ask questions like well
how how well is the mouse doing this
sort of like this task now we can solve
that problem because we designed the
task and we set the mouse to solve it
right and so the um we can sort of say
oh well he's doing he's getting like 95%
correct or let's say he's getting doing
90% correct H but the maximum he could
given the task difficulty the best he
could possibly do is like you know n 98%
or 96% correct like that so that's
comparing the animals Behavior to
Optimal behavior and we do that a lot in
the lab but when it comes to really
complicated things we don't H we don't
have that we lose that ability right and
this is where cognitive psychology comes
in right cognitive psychology is like
okay there's no way in hell a human is
going to solve this really complicated
social dynamics problem optimally in
fact we don't even know how to write
down the solution to this really
complicated social dynamics problem
properly now you might be able to say
from this free energy perspective that
the person is behaving as if they are
solving it probabilistically or as if
they are doing inference but it's not
optimal inference and so now what what
becomes the interesting area of
Investigation the inter area of
Investigation is what are the mistakes
that some someone is making how do we
characterize those like how do we just
characterize their behavior right we
don't have to you know if you're a
psychologist you don't have to commit to
this as inference problem right because
the the question that you want to answer
is not is it doing inference but it's
what sort of you know what sort of
mistakes are you making what sort of
assumptions are you making not which is
a statement about the quality of your
inference algorithm which is much more
interesting than whether or not you're
doing
inference I
that was way more long-winded so I
apologize I meant that to be Compact and
concise just didn't it's a it's a really
no it's a really useful Edition um so
backtracking 15 minutes just for the
audience um the paper that viente
mentioned is I believe uh kof and
colleagues 2018 the mark of blankets
Mark of blankets of life I like just
clarifying that in case people want to
backtrack and um I believe that's the
that's the blankets of blankets one
right yeah that's the one with the
pendulums
clarify that okay this is I mean again
we're getting on far too well um but no
we're doing well we're doing well no no
one shouting at each other yet um okay
no this is this is super so so as you
said Jeff um we kind of need to do
approximate Bays sufficiently well that
we don't dissipate into the heat bu or
it looks like we're doing that um and
that's I I I feel like some of the ways
that issue got skirted is that we would
encode a higher order uh if we're
talking about humans a higher order
prior preference that we believe that we
should be or we are minimizing
variational free energy so there's yeah
no what yeah is that like kind of uh go
ahead go ahead I'm just curious about we
we don't have to believe anything about
this right organ a cell doesn't have to
believe in the free energy principle the
point is is that it's a mathematical
inevitability right it's it you know you
know so you know would so I guess okay
so let me let me go back there are two
ways to think about the free energy
principle and one of them has to do with
like like self-organization so what does
self-organization mean sort of like it
sounds as if you're sort of saying that
like oh I have a notion of
self right that that I act so as so that
that I act that you know I take action
so that my notion of self is
coherent I don't like any of that stuff
um I know that a lot of other people do
but I like because because the whole
point is is that you don't even need a
notion of self right we it you know in
order to behave as if you have a notion
of self right the the way it's
constructed it's sort of like oh okay it
has a boundary the boundary has these
statistics what simply has to happen to
maintain those statistics those
statistics give us a notion of object
type which you could call self and you
could sort of say well okay for now you
know then you could sort of ask the
question well inside does it also have
this notion of self I don't think it's a
meaningful question right it's you know
it's yeah it's sort of like well we've
we we've said like this no you know this
is the object type this is its
definition and we're really asking a
question how do internal and external
States collaborate in order to maintain
the boundary and if you take the if you
take the the max entty you know uh
version of the derivation that becomes
explicit what you're really asking is
how do internal and external States
collaborate to maintain boundary
statistic
has nothing there's no notion of of like
self yes I no I'm completely on board
with that I do uh some of the work that
I like to focus on is actually about
self-modeling self- construction um
which completely is opposed to the
cartisian
ego picture and I think actually a lot
of the conceptual problems come from a
retention of the cartisian ego that
people just feel very it's very
difficult to abandon that picture no I I
was only adding this
because well what you said is very much
in line with what Carl said when he came
on which is that there is no real
existential imperative it's just if you
can see object X at time here and object
X at the same supposed object at t plus
one they've had to have done something
that looks like uh Asian inference so
it's a it's an exponential imperative
only in the sense that we can make the
we can we can kind of say that things
persist through time but there are these
sort of added bells and whistles right
so I you know I'm pretty sure there are
papers now maybe these are earlier
papers which say something like there is
I've read it today there's an a priori
belief now whether this is a
propositional or subpersonal belief I
think is somewhat trivial that I am and
again I'm saying this to make sense I am
the type of thing that will minimize
variational free energy so given that
but given your uh point that we can do
quite shitty dis uh variational basing
inference perceptual inference for one
and AR yeah relative yeah relative to
Optimal but yeah right AR divergences
can be quite big
um what Vicente do you see a way of um
accounting
for the Persistence of the organism
Beyond just like this slow optimization
problem um which as I said kind of
historically at least invoked this high
order prior that I am the type of thing
that will um do desense down free energy
gradients way well I
mean I guess this is a question on how
do things persist in time or how what we
call things persist in time so one thing
is that I don't have any issue with the
with the
mathematical imperative part of it right
that's part of of I mean I can say
something like given this and
this
constraints the uh dynamical system with
an with an attractor will tend to that
to that attractor and that's a
mathematical imperative to right if you
have an attractor with the constraint
may be the system will tell that and
actually you can redescribe that tending
towards the the the attractor in terms
of basan inference in terms of self
self-information minimization whatever
or maximization and free energy right so
I don't have anything about
that
um the thing is is is that the way uh
the permanence of things or the
self-organization of things without the
belief of it has been uh studied in time
uh is is the kind of thing that uh
touches on homeostasis allostasis or
even autop poesis right an activist
think that the thing what the thing does
is to is to self not not only to self
organize but to self uh produce itself
right the the the in so to speak the
internal state of the systems are
engaged in maintaining the boundary
right that's what
they what they what they do there and I
don't think
they they they picture that in terms of
having to believe that they
basically picture that in terms
of catalytic or even physiological ways
to maintain that right um and and I
guess that's that's that's an account of
homeostasis too of allostasis when you
include the dynamical relationship with
the with the with the environment right
so now I guess the question is that to
what extent or the question we at least
we were interested in is to what extent
um this physical imperative of the
minimization of the free energy or the
or the Performing as if making basan
inference is able to capture autop pois
for instance right and not only
autopolis not only the self-organization
part but the self- production
part um and we and that's another
question we have in the yeah so so I
have two I have two answers right uh the
first is is that when it comes to like
maintenance maintenance is baked in
right if you if you say my definition of
a thing is that it has these boundary
statistics and their stationary
statistics it's baked in right you know
which is totally fine that's your
definition of that object type it is
stable right and that you know which is
great the the the hard question and the
question that you know that has been I
think un that has gone largely
unaddressed in the F literature is how
do these things form in the first place
and this is right like you know when you
say like oh it's a um you know the focus
has always been on homeostasis which has
nothing to do with starting from a glob
of
goop right and getting something that is
stable right it doesn't have anything to
do now there's self-repairs in there
right and there is like finding you know
H days and balance with your environment
but there's nothing that is how do I get
from you know a chemical soup to a
cell that is the F has has historically
you know been completely agnostic on
that topic
right um and that's one of the reason
why I don't use words like you know
alost stasis I also forget what they
mean because that's a big word yeah
really big
word um but uh but but but but which but
but that said there are in fact people
working on that particular problem
that's why I like to like like so I've
mentioned Jeremy England like twice now
this he get he get a third mention
that's how cool I think is I also just
read his book which was which was a lot
of fun um and that's probably why it's
on my mind so the approach that he's
taking is well okay so that's the goal
right the goal is to say well what you
know what actually you know why is it
that these that these complicated things
form apparently out of nothing and the
math that he uses is is in fact the
mathematics of statistical physics and
the thing that he and you know and the
mathematical object that seems to
motivate this is constructing free
energy minimizing
flows
right great he even has a love I think
it's chapter seven in his book where he
then goes on to say and by the way you
could think of this you know these free
energy energy minimizing flows as doing
a kind of computation about their
environment but he doesn't actually say
as if I actually read through it twice
just to see if he used the phrase as if
and it turns out he doesn't which is
unfortunate but he makes a very similar
argument right is is that is it you know
this free energy minimization principle
can in fact also lead to the formation
of these
things the math is a lot more
complicated right and certainly static
blankets don't apply in this scenario
like the STA a static Mar blanket
doesn't apply right um because the whole
point is that over time it's actually
forming that blanket is constantly
changing in morphing into a much more
interesting set of statistical that that
so the statistics of the blanket are no
longer stationary so a stationary
blanket doesn't um but the same free
energy principle applies the same free
energy principle that shorting called
negative entropy um uh or that was
sometimes referred to as negative
entropy it's it's and and the reason for
this is because it all fall out
ultimately from like statistical physics
okay fantastic well but yeah but but
you're right that has not really been I
I just wanted to reiterate I did have a
point when I started the tirade I just
want to get back to it um you know it is
true that that hasn't been addressed
like how these blankets actually form in
the first place is the free energy
principle in its current form has been
largely agnostic and that's why we say
well take a look what jerem England's
doing it's basically for energy too okay
I'd like to get to that maybe as our
sort of closing uh remark because don't
think there's going to be too much
antagonism or or Discord there I will
raise one more criticism that was um
mentioned in Ezekiel depalo's
commentaries so this is his criticism of
the FP and and and then we can move on
to the fluffy philosophy or statistical
mechanics whatever it is um so aalo has
two critiques in a way of um this uh of
the Fe formulation the first is exactly
what we've spoken about which is that we
have to make a choice about where to
carve up the Marco blanket and we've
covered that until the cows come home
although I'd be always happy to return
to that but his second point is and I
will quote Marco blankets are too strong
to account for the way the internal
states of an organism are often directly
affected by external states without any
statistical mediation or loss of
Integrity as anyone who's ever been
Tipsy after a few beers or felt dizzy
from heat exhaustion can verify
so now we're kind of we've gone to a
completely different formulation which
is just no
vicarious blanket States okay the we're
having Direct effects um Jeff I'm going
to start with you
because I your face is telling me that
you don't like that so much um how does
that sound to your
ears I I'd have no idea I have no idea
what is meant by
that um it's sort of like I mean
and certainly the analogy that was
provided I do not understand I I suspect
that either I mean I'm probably being
obtuse or maybe I haven't I'm not Tipsy
enough given
analogy um but I don't understand how
anything can have a direct effect I mean
you know I I can think of another
scenario that one might appeal to to
make a similar argument which is like
and I always talk about like protons and
electrons they have electric Fields
right and those fields have you know an
effect right but to my mind that just
means you know your blanket is the
field right
yeah do you have any thoughts on
this
um I
was I was imagining that Jeff was not
going to like that and and and and I do
understand why right I mean it's kind of
in the
in in the very definition of marov
blanket is those sets of states that are
always there kind of you know mediating
between the the internal and the
external I guess that what Ezekiel was
trying to point out
there it's something
like it is possible for those blankets
blankets to be leaky sometimes I think
this is an idea that that you find in
the in the wig Mar cover
blankets um uh paper
too uh oh know that that there's no
there's no
absolute Fusion so to speak between the
internal and the and the and the
external States uh and that's why they
are weak right kind of there's not a
full
encapsulation ah this is just an an
speculation on on on what's a a SLE
point there right that those blanket
maybe can be leaky in some way
sometimes um yeah may maybe this is an
issue that I have difficulty
understanding because I've already moved
on Beyond in my thinking like blankets
don't have to be static yeah right
because because the the best criticism
of of the original set of Mark out
blanket stories was your basic your
definition of a blanket or at least the
way you are using a blanket prohibits
matter transfer between object and
environment so like good luck describing
something that
eats you know
right so fortunately you know you know
the the way around that originally was
to just sort of say oh we could have
like made the blanket operate on fluxes
instead of particles and I never really
liked that you know but but now that
we've gotten this issue where we've
basically said oh no look Dynamic
blankets it all still works right all
the math still works out just fine even
when there's matter transfer it works on
flames and so to my if that was the
ultimate issue then I would say that
issue has been resolved but I would
understand why someone would have drawn
that conclusion from the
literature because the literature
focused on problems that were a lot more
solvable like the dynamic so you know
identifying Dynamic markof blankets is a
really mathematically challenging
problem yeah well like whereas
specifying a static one makes your life
really easy yeah and I you know you know
you should never be overly critical of
people in my view for you know simple
mathemat you know mathematically
mathematical
simplifications right you should always
be generous and say like oh I understand
that's not part of the principle per se
that's just the particular use of it you
know my my favorite example of this is
is like general relativity you know the
the equation of general relativity has
like three terms it's like big G little
G and T what they don't tell you is that
hidden behind those three terms is a ton
of math which is why there's only like
one solution to that problem
right and the same sort of goes for the
free energy principle right if you
actually write down what the objective
function for active inference is it's
really hard to compute yeah and so so
they made a lot of assumptions and to
simplify the math and to make the
computation easier right and so you
should always be I always encourage
people to be generous with devaluating
things in which there's there are
equations and then there's
simplification
you got to if you're evaluating the
theory you got to evaluate the original
equations right and not criticize the
simplifications very christmy um maybe
this will help or uh or not or maybe it
might mudy The Waters Another quote now
from The Mark of blanket trick um
without the mark of blanket formalism
the Dual information geometry would be
reduced to its intrinsic component which
is the only one needed for standard
thermodynamics and I've written next to
that on my notes why don't we just use
this Jeff why don't we just use
this because we want I I really do think
because like at the heart of a lot of
this is like
phenotyping it's sort of like the goal
is actually to segment the universe into
little understand into smaller
understandable
pieces right and since if that's the
goal
that's that's sort of you know I sort of
I feel like I addressed this before when
I said like you know if we could model
the whole universe like no problem like
why would we bother to chop it up in the
little pieces and sort of say oh no this
is a car I'm gonna summarize car
Dynamics I'm gonna worry about the
little bits and part bits and pieces
inside because I could you know why
would you do that if you could just
simulate the whole thing and it was no
problem right so there's sort of this
there's sort of an empirical question
here like that's why the reason we
divide things up the reason we draw
blankets around things is to make our
lives is to make our ability to
understand the universe more tractable
right is to make is to make it easier to
get right the reason why you know it's
like you could always simulate
everything if you could you really can't
but like if you could you would but you
can't right you you're looking for
cognitive shortcuts if you're a
cognitive scientist you're looking if
you're a scientist you're looking for
simplifications of complex systems
you're looking for macroscopic variables
it's it's so it's sort of like there's
an empirical reason why you do that
vient have you got anything to out of
maybe I should have asked exactly what
this claim uh entails what what the
reduction to an intrinsic component
actually looks
like actually I that was uh I wouldn't
say a quote but that
was verbatim almost from from from the
from the Dual
geometry papers right so it was more
than saying
more than focusing in the reduction you
could do I think what what the what what
the the free energy principal proponents
are saying they're like look this is
just thermodynamics extended a little
bit because we have this this this
blanket that they allow us to do this
this all thing right so that's what what
thing and actually I I'm going to one
more time agree with Jeff in many things
uh uh
and I think that again that was that was
kind of the spirit of the Marco blanket
trick to try to go ourself through the
through other things that you need for
for the for the whole building to be
built so to speak and of course you need
to you need to to choose the the the
thing you are interested in you need to
make assumptions on okay these are the
variables I'm going to be working with
and with that I mean uh eological
psychologists are pretty much the first
people that during the 80s started using
dynamical systems theory to to
Model Behavior actually there's a
there's a there's a 1987 book by Peter
kogler and
Michael arvi called information natural
law and rhythmical Behavior if you go
there and read how they gather from
statistical physics and and all that
stuff you see many similar points than
than than you see now in the in in in
the free energy principle right but the
point being when I say okay we we model
or we you know that
within within this kind of dynamic
cognitive science there's a very famous
model the hkb model of couple
oscillators in which the the the main
variable is relative phase why is it
relative phase well it's a it's a
avilable very easy to track and when you
track it and you and you model it you
have a very cool two attractors for
these parameters and you change and and
you see how the how the two attractors
go to one so you you can you can express
the qualitative changes of of the of the
cing of the two oscillator in a very
simple way with just one variable and
you know and but why you pick that one
well because you know it's it it it's
easy and and and it model it well right
so so I mean
I obviously agree with Jeff on that the
point was yes in the literature these
simplification sometimes are not clear
and yeah it's good to to I think they
and and and I also understand yet they
are not clear because the aim was
generality right so we want this to
apply to everything so when when when
the couple oscillators guy come but no
but talk about my thing okay to that's
right yeah we need to put all these
other things us to make it work right so
kind of thing yeah and that's one of the
reasons why I really got to get this
paper out so basically it's it's you
know if you another way to think about
what you know the mark out blanket story
is is that it's it's an integral
component not just of systems
identification Theory but also like
macroscopic physics Discovery right so
why did you pick the phase difference it
was a convenient variable it
encapsulated all of the Dynamics right
what if your problem was I just have a
complex system and I don't know what and
I need to discover what the phase
variables should
be right and the marov blanket story is
one way to do that right it's sort of
like I want to segate my complex system
into different subsystems and if you
have a mark blanket Discovery algorithm
right then it sort of does that for you
it does macroscopic physics
discovery that it identifies that that
was the simplest variable to use that
makes me wonder out of the bloom so I
don't have an answer to this is a pure
question that might not have an answer
when when people who work with dynamical
systems or at least part of them to
model modor control right they they they
gather a lot of ideas from bursting and
from hen and the idea of synergy right
like like the brain is able to to
control the arm as a Synergy because
it's already coordinated uh as a as a as
a whole unit there could you put so
could you put a marov a marov blanket on
a Synergy so to speak I don't know so I
think that that so so to some extent and
so and this is a I'm I'm going to just
sort of say this is a gross
generalization of what the Discover of
what the blanket Discovery algorithm
does but in a in a very real way right
it's doing dimensionality reduction
right which is basically ident Synergy
identification right so why is it that
like you know I can model I can just
sort of look look at all this
complicated stuff I can do well it turns
out right there's really only like a
very small number of variables I have to
track because you know they're all
correlated right there are restrictions
or they're constrained right my wrist is
the same distance for my elbow like and
so on and so that's another way of
character well that means they're
correlated right and Synergy and
correlations are very are sort of you
know are related and so to some extent
what the algorithm actually does or when
you're doing Mark out blanket Discovery
what you're basically saying is what's
correlated what aspects of the dynamical
system are sufficiently strongly related
that I can reduce them to a single
variable right so for example if a rigid
body right I can describe this whole
thing by two points right right I you
know you know I don't have to model
every single molecule in my arm right I
can reduce it to a single Vari and
that's another way of thinking about
like again macroscopic physics Discovery
um right but I also think that's one of
the reasons why like the FP is as it's
formulated is strongly tied to just
empiricism right it's it's it has a lot
to do with just how we do science right
we're we're doing like dimensionality
reduction and looking for principles
that uniformly apply um and and I think
that the focus of the literature has
been on the uniformly AY
thing and now we need to bring it into
the real world of empirical inference
where it's the dimensionality reduction
thing but they are in fact completely
compa amazing uh just again to Lop
around to what I had said so that people
know where to go the quote that I chose
is footnote 12 of the Marco blanket trck
I told you I read the paper um and I
think it pertains to this two
complimentary ways of describing the
density dynamics of internal States one
being this intrinsic uh change over time
towards uh the attractor State and then
the other one is this
extrinsic um tracking of external States
and I'm not a mathematician but it
appears to me that the maths seems
equivalent um and we can actually make a
kind of formal equivalence between those
things which is quite quite beautiful
actually it's it's almost as if they're
equivalent I'm not a mathematician give
me a break um no no no no no sorry that
was that was not a criticism that was a
terrible joke oh okay f f oh right yes
yes very good very good it looks like
they're the
same um yeah excellent so I will finish
with what I promised we'd finish with
which is a kind of bigger potentially
philosophical question that expands
beyond the scope of the free energy
Principle as is right now um and this is
an issue that actually is really matters
to me uh when I first discovered active
inference I remember tweeting two things
one of which was uh the presence of
Markov blankets upon Markov blankets is
the best argument from creation that's
ever been and the second one was um I
think that the apparent distinctions of
internal and external States mediated
for a mark of blanket might itself be an
illusion and there may just be some sort
of singular reality I'm paraphrasing my
tweets but it was more just
philosophical eal thinking and we
mentioned pan psychism
earlier um and again I don't want to get
too into the Weeds on this but Jeff
maybe we could start with you where do
you think this all comes from these um
these distinctions that we can carve for
instrumental reasons which seem to you
know which do work
mathematically and what are your hunches
about what might lie underneath them
I love questions like this and I have
the perfect answer so what lies
underneath
nothing oh that that was my serious face
that doesn't help no no so so I remember
one time I got asked a question like you
know so we're talking about like you
know p's and q's because that's what
you're doing when you're doing
probabilistic reasoning and somebody who
raises their hand like is there a true P
the answer is no no no there's not and
it's not because there isn't a true PE
right it's just I don't understand the
question right it's sort of a it's sort
of a jerky thing to say I I often
describe when I when when I get so as
you might imagine given what I do for a
living I get ask questions like that all
the time and I usually refuse to answer
and the reason I refuse to answer is
because I got up to work today I put on
my coat and tie and I put on my work
pants right my work pants are my harsh
instrumentalist pants and then if you
want me to answer like philosophical or
religious questions it's like well I
have to put on a different pair of
pants right you know when you know when
functioning in this in this environment
like you know it's it it you know I I
take a very very instrumentalist view
right and I think the you know so you
ask like oh do we carve you know is
there some is it all just one thing
right are these artificial carvings AR
the artificial carvings are artificial
right we carve up the world because it's
convenient right because it simplifies
the problems we have to solve it has
empiric it has predictive power and
empirical utility
I like to say that science is not about
truth it is about prediction and data
compression and nothing else right so
when functioning as a scientist that's
what I focus on which is my way of
saying like that's that's my answer
harsh
instrumentalism harsh instrumental means
you don't have to worry about like
what's true I can't wait for all the
philosophers to be shouting at you
virtually um
viente what are your thoughts on
this I was expecting this answer from
Jeff because my preparation to this
podcast was not to reread my own paper
but to to watch another podcast on the
machine learning Street talk I think and
yeah that he was saying electron is just
the name for an equation you know
like right so so I was expecting heart's
instrumentalism I kind I'm kind of an
I'm I'm I'm kind of an instrumentalist
too in some ways
uh but at the same time I'm a realist so
how can that be how can that be the case
right I I guess it's it it comes overall
um comes all to to a form of pragmatism
in the end in which you can be realist
about the kind of things you
do uh and if they are successful well
you you you are dealing with the with
the with the real world and um you do so
by using
instruments and I I'm in favor of
aurality of
instruments uh and marov blankets are
one of them that I I don't personally
use in my own research right but you can
use it um but I wouldn't try to find a
final Foundation like oh there's only
one
thing
um or or you know or everything is such
or everything is such other thing right
it's more like uh we act around um
and reality is somehow the way all where
all our
actions
converge um and not actually sometimes
do sometimes don't and and we we car
reality in that way and all we have is
our our Concepts that are instruments
and are you know not foundational in any
way tools marov blankets other tools and
we go like that but I mean I don't think
there's that there's a there there
there's some form
of you
know matter of fact or fact of of of of
the matter so uh so speak so there's
something that that there's something
that
we some reality that we build up
together through action and is there
it's just it can change so it's not the
final thing it's it's it's it's not the
an old philosopher you know an ancient
philosopher would say something like the
the AR right this this this final
original thing there's no but there's a
thing we do there's there's a there's
there's a matter of fact and and theep
variety of tools and their superposition
and their obus OB obus I don't know that
that that word in English but even the
even the things that they don't match
well tell us thing about what what kind
of thing we can do and we can
do oh where are my Buddhist friends
where are I where my well so that's
that's the funny you asked the wrong
question if you wanted me to put my put
on my Quaker Buddhist pants I can do
that too oh I just generally refuse to
maybe on Christmas day I'll ask it's one
of those it's like
I I remember one of my uh my P one of my
uh one of the faculty in my department
when I was getting my
PhD once said that
um uh philosophy is a lot like like
algebra or or or going to the bathroom
it's just not something you should do in
public I don't agree with
that you
know it it indicates like why it is I
hesitate to answer these questions
because I don't really have good answers
I have my answers and Def faulting to
instrumentalism is like just the easy
way out right sure well yeah they're
purposefully quite provocative and
probing uh but people seem to like
answering them chaps that was uh that
was tremendously fun um maybe we could
have just a couple minutes for closing
remarks um given we've reached such a
beautiful point of conciliation viente
um maybe in addition to sort of closing
remarks you could also let people know
what you're working on and where they
could reach out to you if they wanted to
know more about your topics of
Interest okay so I'm going to
start by by talking one one last time
about the marov blanket trick the paper
kind of grew on its own it's way long I
think it's 24,000 words so it's it's way
it's way longer than I was
expecting uh uh because actually most
most of it is just uh me asking a qu not
me we all of us right but asking the
questions we have right oh but if if the
formalism work why this and why that and
why candle flames and why you know that
kind of thing but I really don't have an
strong uh position on those things I I
just would like to know okay how would
you apply this to a model with a
relative face and that that seems to
include the whole system I only have a
strong opinion with one
thing and which is
uh the fact that
for perception you need or not need
prior knowledge right that's that's
that's actually the real my my real
State there like I
think uh every time you endorse the
system with some prior knowledge in
order to make sense to go as as we talk
from the from the impoverished
impoverished input to the real world so
to speak uh you have no way to justify
that that
that knowledge or to explain what's why
it is there right the typical way you
know what say no it's Evolution right
but it's kind of unsatisfactory for many
I don't want to go to this thing right
but this is actually my only kind of my
my
Ideal breaker I think theories
of perception should then appeal to PRI
your knowledge to explain it and I think
one theory that that does that is
ecological Psychology by virtue of the
lawful relationship between the patterns
of light and the environment you have in
those patterns of light information
enough as to know exactly what the
exactly to to to to to a good the degree
what the what the real environment is
with without the need of pulling other
kind of knowledge into the equation and
I work on that right so so so so part of
my work is is is trying to make sense of
a cognitive Neuroscience that starts
with
ecological psychology for instance if
the brain is not in the business of
inferring the real causes of
impoverished stimulation or of
enriching impoverish stimulation with
other knowledge as to build a model of
the environment what the hell is the is
is is the brain doing right so within
the ecological approach the word uses
resonance the brain resonates to this
richer information and part of my
theoretical work is to try to
operationalize the
resonance metaphors so to speak so how
can we have a a concept that we can
actually test and part of my empirical
work I'm kind of maybe 70% a philosopher
30% a cognitive scientist cognitive
neuroscientist is to try to test that so
this year I've been in in in in the
bmobile lab which is at the technical
University of of Berlin and they and
they specialize in Mobile
EG and so I've been Gathering some
multimodal data that that that has you
know ey tracking motion capture and EG
to try to find what kind of patterns
of information our brain can be
resonating to so how the brain Dynamics
can be constrained by this specific
structors and not just by by by kind of
say simple input and that kind of thing
so I'm trying to yeah last sentence I'm
trying to do something like an
ecological
Neuroscience uh both in the theoretical
realm and the and in the
experimental uh realm very cool very
cool Jeff go
ahead uh
so I'm taking the exact opposite
approach I'm trying to see how far we
can push this whole prior
thing I I like to joke that the the
difference between a basian and a non-
basian is honesty right is you have
priors right I don't know where they
come from I don't know that they're
normative but they're there you you're
kind of stuck with them all knowledge is
like llas all knowledge is based on um
all knowledge is probabilistic right
it's always based on assumptions there
are two sets of assumptions that are
critical to worry about one is I'm going
to get to what I'm doing in a second one
is the data right any conclusions you
draw is conditioned on your observations
but there's another important thing that
we often forget about right is that all
the conclusions draw are also
conditioned on your models for the
universe and I say models this is just
my view I could see vente is going oh my
God no um when I say models I actually
think the most critical thing that we
often neglect when we talk about the
basian brain is that there's not one
model there's a lot of them and they and
and they and and you don't just use one
at a
time right you use lots of in fact you
one you could even think and this is
very coarse I'm I literally am gonna get
to what I'm doing in a second it's very
course but you could think of a basian
brain as having brain regions right and
don't overp parse this because I know
people will right and each region is a
model right each region describes is a
sta statistical model of something and
when you get a new task what do you do
right well you have to figure out which
collection of models and how they're
connected right are the is you know are
the ones that like solve your problem or
model or model the data or describe the
data or compactly summarize this like
the data compression compactly summarize
the information that you received or
give you the predictions about the
things you care about or however you
want to phrase it and so what we're
trying to do right now um is we're
exploring sorry we're exploring the
extent to which we can get this to work
at you know at scale so we want to
construct a brain that's not like some
fast feed forward neural network right
but one that is more brain like right by
summarizing what by saying that no no no
brain has lots of there's lots and lots
and lots of models and the way that the
brain actually attacks problems is by
reasoning by analogy this model explains
this part of what's going on this model
explains this part of what's going going
on and the trick is how do you figure
out how to connect them and so this is a
massive model comparison SL basian graph
neural networking type problem which is
like computationally intensive like
that's
a i' I'd put that in quotes like but it
would like it would be like several sets
that's that's how much scare it is um
that's what we're working on right we're
working on pushing you know seeing how
far we can really push this basum brain
hypothesis but not just sort of saying
there's a prior by saying there's lots
of them and they interact in interest
way and at that point is it still a
prior viente or has it become something
else right I
mean uh this is kind of the of the
agreement I I I I read with with M well
for instance but with other people there
right yeah I mean and I think it is good
I I don't like the the uh the idea of of
of prior knowledge or one prior or many
of them I think there are are other ways
we like to talk about
ecological constraints that are not
inside here out there well but blah blah
blah blah blah
but what I try try try to do is to is no
priors let's see how far I can go and
it's fa that you guys do okay this this
set of of of priors let's see how far
and that's it that's I think that's good
for science actually yeah no that's the
whole point right because eventually
what we want to do is basian model
comparison between your approach and
mine because you know basian is the only
way to do it
obvious I think you guys are gonna
absolute pleasure absolute pleasure
chatting with you well it's no it's been
an absolute pleasure to witness it um
thank you guys for coming on the podcast
and uh I'm sure there are some people
out there devilish people who expected
pots and pounds to be thrown across
webcams but um it I you know this is
what science is about at the end of the
day um finding convergent paths and
trying to get closer to some
approximation of Truth so I hopefully
we've contributed sorry no and you both
Lean Back simultaneously when I said
that word um okay some something that
helps us predict and data comp there you
go Jeff um but thank you guys again from
me and The Institute and uh uh yeah
everyone listening definitely check out
Jeff and vent's work so thank you again
thank you